Starr mss., 1800-1899 LMC 2231
Lilly Library
Starr mss.
19th century
Lilly Library
Starr, Saul, 1907-1964
LMC 2231
3 Boxes 1 standard, 2 custom
1 folio
The Starr mss., 19th century, are holograph copies and originals of vocal and instrumental music and one letter collected by Saul Starr, 1907-1964, physician of Eastchester, New York.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Saul Starr, 1907-1964, was a Brooklyn pediatrician and sheet music collector. He was born in Bayonne, New Jersey and studied at Columbia College. He worked as a pediatrician in Brooklyn for nearly 30 years, where he was visiting pediatrician and director of the children's chronic disease service at Kings County Hospital. He was a collector of American sheet music, with a collection of about 75,000 pieces of music.
Scope and Content Note
The Starr mss., 19th century, are holograph copies and originals of vocal and instrumental music and one letter collected by Saul Starr, 1907-1964, physician of Eastchester, New York. Most of the pieces are undated but appear to belong to the nineteenth century era of transcribing and composing dances and songs for entertainment at home or before local groups. Some compositions are copies of works by Lady John Scott or Anton Wallerstein or of well-known tunes such as Yankee Doodle Dandy and Blue Eyed Mary. Others were efforts by local music teachers or dignitaries such as the French consul at New Orleans, Henri Mérou. The major portion contains two or three sheets, a few are complete albums of music (the oblong music books), and some were parts of larger albums at one time.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 1974, 1979.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series: I. Albums, II. Individual Pieces, and III. Miscellaneous.
Music; Sheet Music; Starr, Saul, 1907-1964
- Starr mss., 46 Items (3 boxes, 1 folder)
  Scope and Contents
  References used were Richard J. Wolfe, Secular Music in America... New York Public Library, 1964 (Lilly ML120 .U5 W8); Oscar Sonneck, A Bibliography of Early Secular Music... Da Capo Press, 1974 (Lilly ML120 .U5 S6 1964); and Grove's Dictionary of Music... London, Macmillan & Co., 1954 (Lilly ML100 .G883 1954).
  - I. ALBUMS. (Box 1)
    - Album beginning Blue Eyed Mary which was published in, and other songs and dances., 1817; (Incomplete, 12 leaves) (Box 1)
      (See Wolfe, 893-905)
    - Album containing Eilleen Allana and Sweet Spirit hear my prayer words in pencil, score in ink., (Incomplete, leaves 342-345) (Box 1)
    - Album, labeled Flauto arranged for flute, piano, and voice, including Hail, Columbia (instrumental only) and Gentle Hallie., (10 leaves) (Box 1)
    - Album, arranged for mandolin, including The Washington Post March with some pieces noted as being copyrighted in and., 1890; 1893; (20 leaves) (Box 1)
    - Album beginning Megen oh oh Megen which was published in., 1799; (Incomplete, leaves 92-121) (Box 1)
      (See Sonneck, page 258)
    - Album beginning Salve Megina del Maestro [Lorenzio Vincenzo] Ciampi [1719-1762]., (Incomplete, pp. 101-104) (Box 1)
    - Album beginning When thou art near me music by Lady John Scott (1810-1900), with one piece dated Naples,., Nov. 10, 1851; (Incomplete, pp. 371-[406]) (Box 1)
    - Album arranged for piano, including Woodville Cotillion and the name of B.E. Ratliff., (Incomplete, 4 leaves) (Box 1)
    - Alice E. Downs, Oberlin, Ohio, Music exercise book including Class Song with separate page of words laid in., (7 leaves) (Box 1)
    - Oblong music book of dances, vols. 1 and 2 as companion volumes containing waltzes, galloppades, cotillions, polkas, schottisches., (14 and 13 leaves) (Box 1)
    - Oblong music book of marches and dances with an index, beginning with a Cotillion by F. Pohlman, including Yankee Doodle with variations on pages 42-43 and having the name Geo[rge] W.B. Felten on the cover., (84pp.) (Box 1)
  - II. INDIVIDUAL PIECES. (Box 2)
    Some of the pieces had been bound in boards with the name of Fannie C. Johnson on the cover.
    - Letter.. Bishop, Sir Henry Rowley. To Windsor, Elizabeth., 1825, July 19 (Box 2)
    - À Toi Romance., (2 leaves) (Box 2)
    - American March in pencil, with the name of W. Naze appended., (1 leaf) (Box 2)
    - L'Anglais au ball!! (Scène comique) Parizot, with the name A. Vulliet appended, the label of the Orphéon Français de la Nouvelle-Orléans Bibliothèque attached and noted as a part of the James H. Snakenberg music collection from Baton Rouge, Louisiana., (3pp.) (Box 2)
    - Auld Robin Gray sung by Miss A. Fenner, Portsmouth, Ohio,., Jan. 3, 1867; (2pp.) (Box 2)
      (See Wolfe 346-353)
    - The Bohemian Polka dated, Anna Edna VanderKiste., 6 May [18]46; (1 leaf) (Box 2)
    - Cantique pour Noël par ADAM dédié à Mademoiselle Marie Woodruff, with appended songs Friendship you canst balm impart... from Guy Mannering and La Serenata del Honduraño arranged by Walter Katte, signed by Mary B. Woodruff,, New York., November 1859; title: Cantique pour Noël,; lb:; title: Friendship you canst balm impart..., (Box 2)
    - Caroussel Polka Miss Mary Hills Catskill with the compliments of W. [Athfo?]., (2 leaves) (Box 2)
    - Chinese Dance & Rondo, composed by M[attias von] Holst (1797-1854)., (4pp.) (Box 2)
    - Della Eve words and music composed and inscribed to Miss Augusta H. Farrar by Benjamin K. Browne., (4pp.) (Box 2)
    - Le Drapeau words by Henri Mérou and music by Antoine Mérou-Grevemeyer, accompanied by a clipping referring to its composition by the wife of the French consul, and an arrangement for voice and piano, from the James H. Snakenberg music collection at Baton Rouge, Louisiana., title: Le Drapeau; lb: (Box 2)
    - German Song., (4pp.) (Box 2)
    - The Gypsie Polka composed and arranged for the Piano Forte by H. Piano and respectfully dedicated to Miss Ann Agusta Chattle of Middletown Orange County, N.Y. (H. Piano, teacher of music)., (2pp.) (Box 2)
    - Let the dead & beautiful rest three verses and chorus, words only., (1 leaf) (Box 2)
    - Mary words by E.L.B., music by Dr. Callcott., (4pp.) (Box 2)
    - Memories, beginning Those dear old songs of home, arranged for four voices, 2 copies signed J.J. Kimball, and one copy copyright by Oliver Ditson Company., Apr. 12, 1892; 1895; lb: (Box 2)
    - "Oh! give me a home if in foreign land" [first line] arranged for voice and piano, in pencil., (4pp.) (Box 2)
    - "O how I love thy law" [first line], arranged for three voices and piano., 3 copies (3pp. each) each in a different hand. (Box 2)
    - "O lone is the spirit on life's troubled ocean [first line].", (1 leaf) (Box 2)
    - "Les pinceaux, la lyre" [first line] and on verso "Is there a heart that never loved.", (2pp.) (Box 2)
    - Polka-Mazurka., (1 leaf) (Box 2)
    - The Ring My Mother Wore words by Louis Dela, music by Mary., (3pp.) (Box 2)
    - Russian Gipsey, Primo and Secundo, Joseph Low, Op. 318., (2 leaves) (Box 2)
    - Solitude Hymn 309, Presbyterian Hymn Book, V[irgil] C[orydon] Taylor (1817-1891)., (1 leaf) (Box 2)
    - The Spinning Wheel by Mrs. D.V.T., arranged by Finlay Dun, beginning "As I sat at my spinning wheel.", (1 leaf) (Box 2)
    - "'Tis Home Where is the Heart is," in pencil., (2 leaves) (Box 2)
    - "A Waltz" in pencil., (1 leaf) (Box 2)
    - The Wedding Polka [Anton] Wallerstein (1813-1892)., (2pp.) (Box 2)
    - Weeping for Thee appended on verso of Romance sans paroles par Medelssohn-Bartholdy., (3pp.) (Box 2)
    - Yankee Doodle Dandy words only., (1 leaf) (Box 2)
    - The Heart bow'd Down by [Michael William] Balfe, for harp, paper watermarked., 1843; (1 leaf) (Box 2)
      (See Grove's 1:370)
    - Ode on Science [words and music by Jezaniah Sumner, ], beginning "The morning shines from the east," autographed by Joseph Snively, September, 1820, 1798; (1 leaf) (Box 2)
      (See Sonneck 311)
    - President Monroe's Walz [sic] by an Amateur, New York [Published by Geib & Co., 23 Maiden, Copyright ]., 1817?; (3pp.) (Box 2)
      (See Sonneck 110)
    - Cradle Song" W.Th. Söderberg. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lullaby Cyril Scott. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Hurrah for Old Go Gertrude Willson, J.M. Davidson. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letter from Normand Music Publishing Company, Worcester, Mass., to E.W. Packard.., July 8, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Niagara Falls by Mrs. Winchell, from Americans and Their Songs by Frank Luther. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letter from Claire Rosenstein of the National Broadcasting Company, Inc., New York, NY, to Saul Starr.., June 2, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - East Hebron Grange Chorus Mrs. E.M. Harris. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Union Hall Schottisch arranged for the Piano Forte and played by W. Wiese's Band at Union Hall Saratoga Springs (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Alleluia l'Amour! Faure. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - The Grave of Bonaparte. A Celebrated Song of the Hutchinson Family. Music by S. Heath. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Fleur de Piquette chansonnette. Le. Orphéon Français de la Nouvelle-Orléans Bibliothèque. James H. Snakenberg Music Collection, Baton Rouge, Louisiana., 25 novembre 1897 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Troy Citizens Corp Quick Step. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Troy Citizens Corp March by P.F. Miller. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - III. MISCELLANEOUS DOCUMENTS. (Box 3)
  - Unlisted/uncatalogued material (Foliobox 25)